Okay, good morning. Today is Thursday, March 15th, it’s the 28th of
אדר. Adar. Today’s דף daf is עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, דף נט,
daf Nun Tet, and we’ll pick up six lines down from the
top of נט עמוד א Nun Tet Amud Aleph with רבי חייא
בר אבא איקלע לגבלא. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba Ikla leGavla. So רבי
חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba went to גבלא, Gavla,
חזא בנות ישראל דמיעברן מעובדי כוכבים שמלו ולא טבלו. chaza bnot Yisrael
de-me-abran me-ovdei kochavim she-malu ve-lo tavlu. He found out that there were
Jewish women there who had become pregnant from non-Jews who were in
the process of converting it seems, who had undergone circumcision but had
not gone to the מקוה. mikveh. That was the one thing he
saw. Second thing he saw, חזא חמרא דמזגו עובדי כוכבים ושתו ישראל.
chaza chamra de-mazgu ovdei kochavim ve-shatu Yisrael. He saw that there was
wine that had been mixed with water by non-Jews which was being
drunk by the Jewish people. We saw yesterday a little bit of
the discussion of whether diluting the wine, mixing the wine, counts as
something that would make the wine יין נסך yayin nesech or not.
חזא תורמוסא דשלקי
להו עובדי כוכבים ואכלי ישראל chaza turmusa de-shalku lehu ovdei kochavim ve-achlei
Yisrael and he saw תורמוסים, turmusim, lupine beans, that were being stewed
by
the non-Jews and the Jewish people were eating it, ולא אמר להו
ולא מידי. ve-lo amar lehu ve-lo midi. And he didn’t say anything
about these three things that he saw. So אתא לקמיה דרבי יוחנן,
ata le-kamei de-Rabbi Yochanan, he came before רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who
was more the מרא דאתרא mara d'asra as if. So אמר ליה,
amar lei, צא והכרז על בניהם שהם ממזרים. tze ve-achriz a-beneihem she-mamzerim.
Go and declare that their children will be ממזרים, mamzerim, that is
the women’s children because these women had become pregnant from non-Jewish men
who had not yet fully converted. We’re going to see, but that’s
a מחלוקת. machlokes. ועל יינם משום יין נסך, ve-al yenam mishum yayin
nesech, and tell them that the wine is יין נסך, yayin nesech,
ועל תורמוסם משום בישולי עובדי כוכבים, ve-al turmusam mishum bishulei ovdei kochavim,
and tell them that the lupine beans are all בישול עכו״ם. bishul
akum.
Because משום שאינם בני תורה. mishum she-einam benei Torah.
Because that is, you should make this announcement because they are not
well educated. So now wait a second, is that, does this mean
you need to educate people because they’re not well educated and so
you need to fill them in on the details? The way the
גמרא Gemara is going to seem to understand it is he was
being unnecessarily strict, at least on one of these cases. So we’re
going to see. But he was being strict because people who are
not בני תורה, benei Torah, people who are not well educated, can
easily mistake between a case that’s permissible and a case which is
not. So now we’ll see. So על בניהם שהם ממזרים. al beneihem
she-mamzerim. Why is it that their children will be considered ממזרים? mamzerim?
רבי יוחנן לטעמיה. Rabbi Yochanan le-taamei. That’s רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan’s position
himself, דאמר רבי יוחנן, de-amar Rabbi Yochanan, לעולם אינו גר עד שימול
ויטבול. le-olam eino ger ad she-yamol ve-yitbol.
Case number one, fact number one we need according to רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan would be that a גר ger is not considered Jewish
until they go to the מקוה mikveh and have circumcision both. That’s
a debate among the תנאים, Tannaim, but the conclusion already in the
אמוראים Amoraim like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is that you need both.
כיון דלא טביל עובד כוכבים הוא, keivan de-lo tavil, oved kochavim hu,
and since he hasn’t gone to the מקוה mikveh he’s considered still
non-Jewish. ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, ve-amar Rabbah bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar
Chana quoted רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת
ישראל הולד ממזר. oved kochavim ve-eved ha-ba al bat Yisrael ha-vlad mamzer.
And this is a debate, but the opinion of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is that if a non-Jewish man and a Jewish woman have
a child, the child is a ממזר. mamzer. ההלכה The halacha is
not like that. ההלכה The halacha according to the vast majority of
the ראשונים Rishonim as far as I understand is that if a
non-Jewish man and a Jewish woman have a child, הולד כשר. ha-vlad
kasher. The child is considered to be a kosher Jew and the
only question is whether such a person, if it’s a girl, whether
she could marry a כהן kohen or not. That’s more the question,
whether there’s a פגם לכהונה pegam le-kehuna or not. But the child
would be considered Jewish. So here, I mean, a ממזר, mamzer, by
the way, ממזר mamzer is Jewish, but a ממזר mamzer is disqualified.
So it becomes interesting, how is it that having a Jewish mother
makes you Jewish enough that you’re Jewish, but there’s still a problem
of ממזרות? mamzerut? Because what kind of prohibitions create ממזר? mamzer? So
is it, ההלכה the halacha that we, the conclusive הלכה halacha is
that the only types of relationships that create ממזרות mamzerus are those
which are prohibited either with כרת kareth or with capital punishment. So
a relationship for a Jewish woman with a non-Jewish man is not
punishable by that severe degree and therefore the child would not be
a ממזר. mamzer. וגזרו על יינם משום יין נסך, ve-gazru al yenam
mishum yayin nesech,
so
and you should declare that their wine is יין נסך, yayin nesech,
משום לך לך אמרין נזירא סחור סחור לכרמא לא תקרב. mishum lech
lech amrin nezira sechor sechor le-charma lo tikrav.
Because we tell the נזיר nazir to avoid the vineyard, that is
this is the general principle of even many of the laws of
the דרבנן d'rabbanan סתם יינם stam yeinam is that the recommendation is
to avoid as much as possible any closeness, even any possible risk,
better to just stay clear, right? And and of course the evocative
imagery of telling the נזיר Nazir to walk around the vineyard, there
it even has a proof in ספר שופטים Sefer Shoftim where שמשון
Shimshon goes and fights the lion. It says he went down to
go to Timnah with his parents together. And then it says that
he encountered the lion and he was alone. So why did he
fight the lion alone? Where were his parents? Well the answer is
the previous פסוק pasuk said that they were going between the כרמים.
kramim. So already in the time of שמשון, Shimshon, or שמשון Shimshon
even, he had enough שכל sechel to know to avoid even going
near the vineyard. He went around, he took a longer path and
that's where he came across the lion somewhere up in the mountains
or something and his parents were off somewhere else. And that's why
they didn't know about the honey and that's blah blah blah blah
blah the whole rest of the שמשון Shimshon story. So we say
לך לך אמרי נזירא סחור סחור לכרמא לא תקרב. Lech lech amri
Nazira schor schor l'charma lo tikrav. I don't know why I have
to say it such a long sentence. At the end of the
day it's just לכרמא לא תקרב, l'charma lo tikrav, don't go near
the vineyard. But it becomes this sort of statement. והתורמוסן משום בישולי
עובדי כוכבים V'haturmusan mishum bishulei ovdei kochavim
and what about the fact that their תורמוסים, turmusim, their lupine beans
will be considered בישול עכו"ם bishul akum לפי שאינן בני תורה? lefi
she'einan bnei Torah? So it's because they're uneducated. So what does that
mean? So we're going to say so טעמא דאינן בני תורה, ta'ama
d'einan bnei Torah, is it the reason why you should tell them
that the beans are בישול עכו"ם bishul akum is only because they
don't actually know the הלכה, halacha, but הא בני תורה שרי, ha
bnei Torah shari, would it really be true that if they were
well educated you would be able to tell them that these beans
are okay to eat? והאמר רב שמואל בר רב יצחק אמר רב,
V'ha'amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak amar Rav, והאמר רב שמואל בר
רב יצחק קודם רב, V'ha'amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak kodem Rav,
כל שנאכל כמות שהוא חי אין בו משום בישולי עובדי כוכבים.
kol shene'echal kamoshehu chai ein bo mishum bishulei
ovdei kochavim. So number one possibility is maybe the principle that's being
debated here is well it sounds like these beans are not able
to be eaten raw, they're very bitter, they have a strong flavor.
If you look in רש"י, Rashi, no רש"י Rashi doesn't say it.
But we know from other places the what? He does, you're right.
He does? Oh, תורמוס אינו נאכל כמות שהוא חי, Turmus eino ne'echal
kamoshehu chai, right. The second to last line in רש"י Rashi that
תורמוסים, turmusim, the beans we know from מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbat, the
main סוגיא sugya about בורר borer discusses cooking the beans, the תורמוסים
turmusim with their peels, with their shells in order to somehow soften
the bitter flavor and then having to separate the beans away from
the peels. So here too it's a little bit of a cryptic
סוגיא, sugya, but here we have כמות שהוא חי kamoshehu chai so
אין בו משום בישולי עובדי כוכבים. ein bo mishum bishulei ovdei kochavim.
One of the most important principles for the laws of בישול עכו"ם
bishul akum is that foods which can be or are regularly eaten
raw do not have the הלכות halachot of בישול עכו"ם. bishul akum.
That is, so if it's something which you could eat raw anyway,
a carrot, a tomato, apples, those kinds of things are not going
to have problems of בישול עכו"ם, bishul akum, which frees up a
great possibility. Now there are many things which are only edible cooked:
meat, rice, beans, usually like dry beans, things like that. So at
least this criterion covers one slice of the vegetable world certainly. And
part of the question becomes well what about now that sushi has
become so common, does that make it so that all fish or
many types of fish would be considered נאכל כמות שהוא חי ne'echal
kamoshehu chai and therefore a cooked piece of fish will not have
a problem of בישול עכו"ם? bishul akum? It's a very interesting question
and some פוסקים poskim say yes and some פוסקים poskim say it
depends which grade of fish, if it's a very high quality fish
they would use for sushi it's one thing, but if it's a
fish that you could only eat cooked, then maybe not. Okay. רב
יצחק בר אשי אמר
רב שמואל קודם רב? Rav Yitzchak bar
Ashi amar
Rav Shmuel kodem Rav?
רב יוחנן כי הך לישנא סבירא ליה. Rav Yochanan ki hach lishana
sevira leh.
So רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan holds like that opinion and therefore that
can't be the reason that it can't be they would only say
the תורמוסים turmusim are בישול עכו"ם bishul akum because they're not בני
תורה. bnei Torah. דאמר רב שמואל בר רב יצחק אמר רב, D'amar
Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak amar Rav, כל שאינו עולה על שולחן
של מלכים ללפת בו את הפת אין בו משום בישולי עובדי כוכבים.
kol she'eino oleh al shulchan shel melachim l'lafet bo es hapas ein
bo
mishum bishulei ovdei kochavim. Second criterion for the laws of בישול עכו"ם
bishul akum is that it has to be something which is literally
the way it's phrased here: עולה על שולחן של מלכים, oleh al
shulchan shel melachim, to go up to be served at the table
of kings, ללפת בו את הפת, l'lafet bo es hapas, as a
side dish, as something which is eaten as part of a meal
with bread.
לפת Lefet we know like is a dip, ללפת בו את הפת,
l'lafet bo es hapas, whatever you dip the bread in, which means
sort of the general eating culture of the time, it's eaten at
the meal as part of the meal. So this question becomes how
literally do we take ללפת בו את הפת l'lafet bo es hapas
also? What about things which even if you eat them during the
meal you would never put them on the bread?
Rice, let's say, right? Something like that. One possibility. But also what
how do we determine the criterion of עולה על שולחן של מלכים?
oleh al shulchan shel melachim? What what is considered high quality enough
or fresh enough or nice enough and fancy enough that it would
be served to the king? So a certain of the kashrut agencies
at least in the United States, we don't have a king, but
they find out like what gets served at the... served at the
White House state dinners and things like that. Steak with ketchup. Steak
with ketchup, right, well a grilled steak a grilled steak certainly would
be considered עולה על שולחן מלכים oleh al shulchan melachim because that's
a cut of meat it's well prepared whatever.
But would a hot dog be considered עולה על שולחן מלכים? oleh
al shulchan melachim? Hot dogs are pre-cooked anyway. But you know something
like that, the question would become at what determination? So potato chips
certainly is a snack, not served at a meal, so that's also
something, right? Potato chips are a fried potato, they're not edible raw,
but they're not first of all they're not fancy enough and second
of all they're never eaten as part of a meal, they're eaten
as a snack. So that also would change. And in fact if
you think about it, if it's not עולה על שולחן מלכים, oleh
al shulchan melachim, it's never served as part of a meal, so
you could imagine at least certain types of street foods, popcorn and
nuts and things get discussed by the אחרונים achronim even you know
in times before there was a you know a non-Jewish vendor is
selling roasted chestnuts and there's oil and there's chestnuts and there's salt
and that's the ingredients or whatever. Maybe there's a lot of room
to say that there would be reason to say that that would
be permissible.
Okay, so maybe that's the reason that it's עולה על שולחן מלכים
ללפת בו את הפת. oleh al shulchan melachim l'lafet bo et hapat.
So טעמא דאינן בני תורה הא בני תורה שרי. taama de'inan bnei
Torah ha bnei Torah sharei. So maybe the reason why the determination
would be that if they're not בני תורה bnei Torah
we'll insist that even something like תורמוסין turmosin beans, תורמוסין turmosin beans
are not the nicest kind of beans, right? We said they have
this bitter aftertaste whatever they're relatively cheap. So the reason why that
technically they would be permitted
but who is it? רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. No, not רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. Who was talking to רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? Was רבי
אבא? Rabbi Abba? No, was רבי חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba. So רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba wants רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to declare them prohibited nonetheless because he would say
oh they're not בני תורה bnei Torah so we don't have to
let them in on this secret that if it's not עולה על
שולחן מלכים oleh al shulchan melachim it'd be permissible because he doesn't
want to confuse them. He'll be like they'll say one kind of
beans is permissible and one kind of beans isn't, it'll get very
confusing for them. Okay, so בני תורה שרי. bnei Torah sharei.
So בעא מיניה מרבי יוחנן? ba'a minei miRabbi Yochanan? No. It was
רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba who said that.
Yes. There was... which one?
רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba asked רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan gave the reasons why.
No, the שאינן בני תורה. she'einan bnei Torah.
Oh you're right. No. אתא לקמיה דרבי יוחנן. ata lekamei diRabbi Yochanan.
He came to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Right. And he said פוק
ואכריז pok v'achrez on these three things. He he told רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan you're the מרא דאתרא, marda'asra, you should make this proclamation.
Oh I see. Please announce to the people
the
children are ממזרים, mamzerim, the wine is ייין נסך, yayin nesech, and
the beans are...
but רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to him go announce
according to this.
That doesn't make sense.
No. He came he came to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and told
him what he found and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to him
go announce.
I'm not sure. Anyway. It certainly fits with רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan
position. The story makes sense. The position would make sense with the
story. Anyway, doesn't matter. Okay, so בעו מיניה מרב כהנא. be'u minei
meRav Kahana. So they asked רב כהנא: Rav Kahana: עובד כוכבים מהו
שיוליך ענבים לגת? oved kochavim mahu sheyolich anavim legat? A new case.
Can a non-Jewish person transport the grapes from the vineyard from wherever
the grapes have been harvested to the גת, gat, to the wine
press, to the pressing area?
Okay so what's going to be the problem is that there'll be
some drips of juice that start squeezing out of the grapes and
get the grapes all wet with the juice and then this non-Jewish
person is transporting a volume of juice. So אמר להו אסור משום
לך לך אמרי נזירא סחור סחור לכרמא לא תקרב. amar lehu assur
mishum lech lech amri nezira s'chor s'chor l'charma lo tikrav. That we
say it's prohibited not necessarily because of any technical reason it sounds
like right? It sounds like just sort of a general rule of
safeguarding around wine. Right? That's what this line comes to indicate. לך
לך אמרי נזירא, lech lech amri nezira, we say avoid everything as
much as possible. So איתיביה רב יימר לרב כהנא. itivei Rav Yeimar
leRav Kahana. רב יימר Rav Yeimar contradicted רב כהנא Rav Kahana from
this תוספתא: tosefta: עובד כוכבים שהביא ענבים לגת בסלין ובדודורין.
oved kochavim
shehevi anavim legat basalin uvadodorin. A non-Jew who transports
the grapes to the גת gat either in baskets or in דודורין
dodorin which רש"י Rashi says גיגיות קטנות, gigiyot ketanot, some other kind
of baskets or pails of some kind. So אף על פי שהיין
מזלף עליהם מותר. af al pi shehayayin mezalef aleihem mutar. Even though
the grape juice really not wine at this point but grape juice
drips out of the grapes onto the other grapes and it's dripping,
מזלף, mezalef, מותר, mutar, it's permissible. So that תוספתא tosefta sounds like
a non-Jew is permitted to transport it and there's no problem. So
אמר ליה
הבי קאמרת
אנא לכתחילה קאמינא.
amar lei hevi ka'amart
ana lechatchila ka'amina. So the difference is because the תוספתא tosefta that
you quoted said in a case where the non-Jew brought it, right?
It says עובד כוכבים שהביא. oved kochavim shehevi. That's only בדיעבד. bedi'eved.
In a case where it had happened already, post facto, then it's
permissible post facto. But we wouldn't encourage you or allow you to
do it ab initio, לכתחילה, L'chatchila, because we say לך לך אמור
לנזירא. Lech lech amor l'nezira. That is the whole notion of the
safeguard is not because there's a real concern of anything going to
happen, but because we want to keep non-Jews out of the wine
production as much as possible, which again raises other kinds of questions
about in nowadays, you know, whatever it is, Welch's grape juice has
a הכשר Hechsher now, but before they had a הכשר, Hechsher, like
they probably didn't change their production very much. So at what point
they collect the grapes with some huge harvesting machine or whatever, and
then they transport them to a factory and they dump them into
a big thing and a robot crushes them and the robot bottles
the juice. Maybe there's no problem at all with Welch's grape juice
originally, but maybe we still say this whole general notion of לכרמך
לא תקרב, L'charmecha lo tikrav, don't, don't get involved in non-Jewish production
of grape juice and wine even if there's no real risk involved.
Okay. ההוא
אתרוגא דנפל לחביתא דחמרא, Hahu etroga d'nefal l'chavita d'chamra, and an etrog
fell into a barrel of wine. Okay,
so אידרי עובד כוכבים ושקליה, Idrei oveid kochavim v'shaklei, the non-Jew wanted
to reach in and grab the etrog to take it out of
the wine. So אמר להו רב אשי, Amar lehu Rav Ashi, so
it's a little bit unclear, the grammar makes it sound like he
did that, but the way Rav Ashi gives this recommendation, it sounds
like he was about to do it and they were able to
stop him. So I'm not 100% sure. אמר להו רב אשי, Amar
lehu Rav Ashi, Rav Ashi said to them, נקטוה לידיה, Naktua l'yadei,
like immobilize his hand, keep his hand in place so he doesn't
כי היכי דלא לשכשך ביה, Ki heichi d'lo l'shachsheich bei, so that
he won't stir it, right? Because we know that stirring is a
big problem.
His hand's inside but he can't move it?
A bit unclear.
וברצויה עד דשייפא, U'virtzuya ad d'shaifa, and then tilt the barrel to
pour out the wine until he grabs, it flows, the etrog goes
into his hand. That is, the wine will be pouring into some
other container. אמר רב אשי האי עובד כוכבים דנסכיה לחמרא דישראל בכוונה.
Amar Rav Ashi hai
oveid kochavim d'naschei l'chamra d'Yisrael b'chavana. What about a case where a
non-Jew goes to my house and takes a bottle of wine that
I was saving for Friday night קידוש Kiddush and pours it out
as a libation to Zeus? Okay,
so he came into my house and took my property and has
made it יין נסך, Yayin nesech, real יין נסך, Yayin nesech, not
even סתם יינם. Stam yeinam. So אף על גב דלזבוניה לעובד כוכבים
אחרינא אסור, Af al gav d'l'zavunei l'oveid kochavim acharina assur, even though
it's prohibited now to sell it to another non-Jew because it's אסור
בהנאה, Assur b'hana'ah, so I can't get any financial benefit from it,
שרי ליה למשקל דמי מההוא עובד כוכבים. Shari lei l'mishkal dmei mehahu
oveid kochavim. It's permissible for me to claim the damages from him
in court. So this is very interesting, that is, even though the
process will be the same, he got a bottle of wine and
I get the value of a bottle of wine, so it's like
I sold it to him, like a retroactive sale, but it's not
a retroactive sale. It's him, I'm suing him for damages, and that's
a different transaction which fundamentally is more removed from the איסור הנאה
Issur hana'ah of the wine itself. So when you think about the
process of claiming for damages, and this is a good מסכת נזיקין
Masechet Nezikin question, when you claim damages from someone in court, it's
not that you're, that they're buying it from you retroactively, right? I
killed your cow, and now I'm paying you for it. So retroactively
it's as if it was my cow when I killed it. That's
not how it works. It's actually there's a whole different notion,
separate from ownership, there's the notion of damages and compensation for damages
happens to be coincidentally, coincidentally, assessed at the rate of how much
it would cost to replace it, but it's not because the person
is retroactively buying the rights to have it.
I have lawyers in the room, I'm sure you have interesting thoughts
about this as well. But so,
so that frees up the Jewish person the right to be able
to still to claim the damages even from something which is אסור
בהנאה. Assur b'hana'ah. There's a lengthy essay which has been printed in
the back of the תשובות הריב"ש Teshuvot HaRivash all about how much
people are or not owners of things which are themselves אסור בהנאה.
Assur b'hana'ah. So for a great example, of course, is חמץ בפסח,
Chametz b'Pesach, right? חמץ בפסח Chametz b'Pesach is אסור בהנאה, Assur b'hana'ah,
you're not allowed to sell, you're not allowed to own חמץ Chametz
or sell חמץ Chametz or feed חמץ Chametz to your animals or
anything, right? So at the same time, the Torah has מצוות Mitzvot
of בל יראה ובל ימצא, Bal yeira'eh u'val yimatzei, that it's not
you're not allowed to own the חמץ Chametz in your possession. So
wait a second, if I can't get any הנאה Hana'ah from it,
what does it mean for me to own it? So it's a
special חידוש Chidush that the Torah counts it as if you own
it, even though really you can't own it because it's worthless, because
it's useless, because it's אסור בהנאה. Assur b'hana'ah. So it gets into
some very interesting questions. What about if you write a גט Get
on איסורי הנאה? Issurei hana'ah? What if you write contracts on איסורי
הנאה, Issurei hana'ah, all these kind of things of, you know, the
skin of an animal that was from עיר הנדחת Ir Hanidachat or
something like, you know, far-fetched cases, but it becomes interesting to consider
how far do we take the notion that something
is
אסור בהנאה. Assur b'hana'ah. or useless at this point, becomes interesting. Okay.
So מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reasoning for רב אשי? Rav
Ashi? So מקלא קלייה, mikla kalei, it's like he burned it up.
That is, it's not that he's buying the wine, it's that having
made it into יין נסך, yayin nesech, it was as if, imagine,
he had totally destroyed the wine, but he still has to compensate
you for the damage. Okay. אמר רב אשי מנא אמינא לה דתניא.
Amar Rav Ashi m'na amina lah ditanya. So where do I learn
this from? Why do I have this position? And it's interesting that
it's אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, so it's like a new
statement from רב אשי, Rav Ashi, but it's מנא אמינא לה, m'na
amina lah, where did I learn this from? So it's also interesting.
דתניא, Ditanya, it's from this ברייתא. braita. עובד כוכבים שנסך יינו של
ישראל שלא בפני עבודת כוכבים. Oveid kochavim she'nasach yeino shel yisrael shelo
bifnei avodat kochavim.
A non-Jewish person, an idol worshiper, poured out the libation for this
idolatrous religion, but שלא בפני עבודת כוכבים, shelo bifnei avodat kochavim, not
in the presence of the idol itself. אסור, Assur, the wine still
becomes prohibited. ורבי יהודה בן בבא ורבי יהודה בן בתירא מתיר. V'Rabbi
Yehuda ben Bava v'Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira matir. But these two other
תנאים tannaim disagree with the תנא קמא tanna kamma quoted in the
ברייתא braita and say actually it's permissible. משום שני דברים, Mishum shenei
devarim, because there are two rationales for leniency. We're going to see
רב אשי Rav Ashi is מחמיר, machmir, right? He says the wine
is prohibited. But he relies on the two leniencies of רבי יהודה
בן בבא Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava and רבי יהודה בן בתירא Rabbi
Yehuda ben Beteira to justify the claim in court, the claim of
the damages. So it's interesting. He adopts actually an intermediate position between
the תנאי tannai positions. אחד שאין מנסכין יין אלא בפני עבודת כוכבים.
Echad she'ein menaschin yayin ela bifnei avodat kochavim. One is because this
doesn't really count as a נסך, nesech, it doesn't really count as
a libation if it's not in the physical presence of the idol
itself. That is, okay, so you did it לשם עבודה זרה, leshem
avodah zarah, you did it with the intention that you're worshiping this
idol, but there's no idol there. ואחד שאומר לו לא כל הימנך
שתאסור ייני לאונסי. V'echad she'omer lo lo kol himencha she'te'asor yeini l'onsi.
And the second is that the owner can say, "You have no
right to forbid my property to me
against my will." That is, the general claim which is
אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו. ein adam oser davar she'eino shelo.
Obviously, I mean, if you say like, I'm cooking steak, somebody comes
in and drops a pat of butter on top, you can't say,
oh, you know, אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו. ein adam oser
davar she'eino shelo. Obviously, it's milk and meat. There's no getting around
the physical reality. So עבודה זרה avodah zarah is somewhere in the
middle, which is that there's no physical change to the wine. It's
only a status change, right? The wine is still wine, it just
happens now to be יין נסך. yayin nesech. But the Jewish person,
so you get still enough of a claim or enough of an
ability to claim that it's not within your rights. You have no
right to come into my house and take all my wine and
turn it into a יין נסך. yayin nesech. So that secondary claim,
the two claims together were what motivated רבי יהודה בן בבא Rabbi
Yehuda ben Bava and רבי יהודה בן בתירא Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira
to be lenient. That is, number one, it doesn't really count as
a נסך nesech if it's not in the presence of the idol
itself, and number two,
that really you're doing it against the owner's will and we should
say אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו, ein adam oser davar she'eino
shelo, a person can't make prohibited something which doesn't belong to them.
And therefore, in combination those two together,
according to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, he wasn't willing to take it
so far to say the wine will be permitted to drink or
to sell, but he does say it enough that he's willing to
allow you to make a claim of damages in court. An intermediate,
yeah.
No,
it's interesting because yesterday Rabbi Linzer drew our attention to a תוספות
Tosafot on עבודה זרה נג.
Avodah Zarah nun gimmel.
Oh, yeah. I mean, it's very interesting, it has a lot of
reality in it. But basically, it's the פסק psak of the תוספות
למעשה Tosafot l'ma'aseh that if a non-Jew דוקא davka comes and sticks
their hand in your wine, then you're allowed to sell it to
other non-Jews. מותר בהנאה. Mutar behana'ah. Right.
No, he could also drink it, he said. If a fellow drank,
I don't know
where,
yeah, yeah, it's תוספות כתב הרי. Tosafot katav ha-Ri.
כתב הרי, Katav ha-Ri, yeah.
In the second to last at the bottom. וכן כתב בתשובה. V'chen
katav bitshuva.
מותר
למוכרו לעובדי כוכבים Mutar lemochro l'ovdei kochavim דלא בקיאי בשיכשוכא. de'lo baki
b'shichshucha. Okay. אבל בשתייה אסור. Aval b'shtiya assur. It's prohibited to drink
it. Okay.
ודוקא שלא נתכוון
מיהא כדי להכעיס. V'davka shelo nitkaven miha k'dei l'hach'is.
ובפסקי ריב"א וכן מוכח הסוגיה קרוב הדבר בעיני דאפילו אם נגע עובד
כוכבים בידו להכעיס מותר בשתייה.
U'v'piskei Riva
v'chen
mochiach hasugya karov hadavar be'einai d'afilu im naga oveid kochavim beyado l'hach'is
mutar b'shtiya.
Right. If he did it to get you angry, not for any
religious purpose, you could even drink it.
פסקי ריב"א. Piskei Riva.
Very interesting, very interesting.
It's, I mean,
in this תוספות Tosafot there, in the פסק, psak, completely ignore, maybe
the שו"ת מדבר Shut Medubbar refers to this next דף, daf, but
this is a far
more, goes far further
because of that אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו ein adam oser
davar she'eino shelo principle is another reason to be lenient.
I mean, you could say the reality is different, where here they
could say to you,
here you really did an act of worshiping. So then you need
some, right, but it becomes
another solution is more available because here it seems like you could.
עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim and רב אשי Rav Ashi says that you
can say, "Pay me." Right.
"Pay me" is an easier claim
to make like the Crusaders, right, that are like...
But again, who are you... can you really take this idol worshipper
to court or whatever, it becomes more difficult.
We'll do it maybe a little bit more,
but I also need to go downstairs so if anything it'd be
good to end early. Okay. And I'll be doing tomorrow as well.
Tomorrow's דף daf is longer so we'll try to go a little
bit further. Okay.
ההיא חביתא דחמרא דאשתקיל ברזא. Hahi chavita d'chamra d'ishtakil barza. There was
a barrel of wine that the spout had been taken out. Okay.
אתא עובדי כוכבים אדריה ata ovdei kochavim adrei אנח ידיה עליה. anach
yadei alei. So the non-Jewish person came over to it and he
put his hand over it. Okay. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa,
כל דלהדי ברזא חמרא אסיר. kol d'lahadei barza chamra asir.
Whoever דלהדי, d'lahadei, whoever takes out the spout of the wine, אסיר,
asir, prohibits it. Okay. ואידך שרי. V'idach shari.
So and he's disagreeing that it should be permissible. Okay, and רש"י
Rashi says אף בשתיה, af b'shtiya, he said even permissible to drink.
ואיכא דאמרי אמר רב פפא, V'ika d'amri amar Rav Papa, there's a
different version of what רב פפא Rav Papa said. אמר רב פפא,
Amar Rav Papa, עד הברזא חמרא אסיר. ad habarza chamra asir. In
the barrel up until the point where the spout is, that is
what... You know what, let's just do this tomorrow, I have to
deal with this בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah downstairs and everything else. So,
I know it's a short day, but we're going to do plenty
tomorrow. Okay, have a great day.